Guide to the Ernst Levy Papers 1919-2004
University of Chicago Library
Levy, Ernst. Papers
1919-2004
9.75 linear feet (8 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Ernst Levy (1895-1981), composer and professor of music at the University of Chicago (1951-54). Papers include musical scores and many significant written academic works, including a French manuscript of his book A Theory of Harmony. Public and biographical items include an extensive radio broadcast interview, late interest and news articles mentioning Levy and significant correspondence, biographical information, catalogs of released recordings and copies of catalogued records from European libraries.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Ernst Levy was a prolific composer and arranger of music, author and piano virtuoso. He served on the faculty at the University of Chicago from 1951 to 1954..
Levy was born in Basel, Switzerland November the 18th, 1895. He studied with Raoul Pugno, Egon Petri and Basel Conservatory mentor and colleague Hans Huber. In Basel Levy taught extensively, becoming Huber's successor of the virtuoso class at the Conservatory in 1917.
Moving to Paris in 1925, Levy continued to teach and perform, and in 1928 founded the first major chorus in Paris, the Choeur Philharmonique, who premiered performances and recordings of notable works by Brahms and Liszt.
For political reasons, Levy moved to Boston in 1941, teaching at the New England Conservatory of Music until 1945. The next twenty five years were spent teaching piano and composition, conducting choral and orchestral works, all the while composing an impressive amount of work, many included in this collection. In addition to his time in Boston and Chicago; he spent time at Bennington College in Vermont (1946-51), at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1954-59) and the Brooklyn College of the City University of New York (1959-66). Levy then retired from teaching, returning to Switzerland in 1966.
Levy became well known and is remarkable in his innovative approach and interpretations of musical works, in addition to his integration of art, science and philosophy into the performance and composition of musical works.
Levy died on April 19th, 1981 in Morges, Switzerland at the age of eighty-five.
Scope Note
Series I of the Ernst Levy papers contain public and biographic items, including correspondence and an interview during his final years (1979-81), biographical notes and essays, and copies of French and German catalogues of his works.
Levy's academic career produced a number of writings and lectures, many of which are collected in Series II. An original and copy of one of his major publications in French – A Theory of Harmony, published posthumously in 1985, is also included here.
Series III of the Ernst Levy papers consist of a significant number of musical compositions, mostly in original score format, from his first string quartet in 1919 to his final sonatas in 1980. Many works contain notes by the composer - typed and attached to the inside front or back cover of the work, usually discussing the nature of the work or performance notes. Most works are original, bound scores kept as reference copies by the composer. A few are published copies, a few appear as copies or photocopies of originals, and a few are handwritten original scores.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Levy, Ernst, 1895-; Composers; Piano Music
INVENTORY
- Series I: Public and Biographical
  - Public and biographical documents, University of Chicago Concert Program, 1952 French newsletter Musique, 1971 Swiss news article from Basler Zeitung, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview with Bernard Falciola, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Public and biographical documents, Final living correspondence with Morgan and Schubel, 1979-1981 Correspondence with Thuring Bram (German), 1981 Photocopy of Newspaper Article Mentioning Levy and Morgan, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Public and biographical documents, Opus One (record label) release catalog and record jacket notes, 1983 Richmond Symphony concert program with biographical note, 1994 Compact disc release notes and biographic essays, 1997 Correspondence with Ward Marston (record label), 1997-2004 Correspondence with Wolfgang Rathert, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Public and biographical documents, Catalogue of written and musical works (French), undated Photocopies of card catalogue of works (German), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Writings and Lectures
  - Notes on the 10th and 11th symphonies, 1944, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "A New Pythagorean Investigation of Harmony", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "How A Composer Works" (multiple drafts), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Elizabethan Ayre", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Medieval Proportion Canons" (draft), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Birth, Growth and Shaping of Musical Ideas" (draft and final), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Changes of Style Since Bach", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Formative Forms and Forming Principles", 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings, 1965, undated, "Definitions" article in Musique (French Conservatory of Music), 1965 Academic outline of course "The Symphony for Musical Illiterates", undated "On the Concept of Variation" academic treatise, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A Theory of Harmony, 1985, Original French manuscript Copy of French manuscript (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Musical Compositions
  - String Quartet One, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Compositions, 1918-1948, "Schlafe du" (song), 1918 "Jetzt brennen deine heissen Kusse" (song), 1918 Sonata for Violin and Piano (published sheet music), 1932 Cantata on Ecclesiastes, 1945 "Pastorale", 1946 Four Folk Songs from Switzerland, 1946 "Fanfares" (score), 1947 Cantata No. 2 (two copies), 1948 "Hear Ye Children" (three copies), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Eleventh Symphony, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cantata No. 3, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Twelfth Symphony, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Compositions, 1952, Divertimento for Clarinet and Piano, 1952 Theme and Transformations for Clarinet and Piano, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - First Trio for Violin, Viola and Violoncello (2 copies), 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sonata for Violoncello and Piano, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sonata for Horn and Piano, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Dreizehnte Symphony, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Suite for Viola or Violoncello, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Third Suite for Orchestra, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Compositions, 1957-1958, Suite for Orchestra, 1957 Trio Fantasy, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Compositions, 1959-1960, Fourth Suite for Orchestra, 1959 Suite for Violin, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Second Trio, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Compositions, 1960, "Summer Music", 1960 "Meditatio", 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Compositions, 1961-1962, Second Sonata for Violin and Piano, 1961 Third Sonata for Violin and Piano, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Compositions, 1962, Sonatina for Violin and Piano, 1962 Second Sonatina for Violin and Piano, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Fourteenth Symphony, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Compositions, 1963, Suite for Two Violas (2 copies), 1963 Trio for Clarinet, Violoincello and Piano, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Gandamus" including premiere program, 1964-65 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Compositions, 1964-1965, Third Sonatina, 1964 Fourth Sonatina, 1964 Sonata for three violin parts, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Compositions, 1966-1968, Troisieme Trio a Cordes, 1966 "Le Desir des Justes", 1968 "Chanson Triviala", 1968 Motet for Mixed Choir, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Trio for Clarinet, Viola and Piano, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - A Musical Gathering, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Second Trio for Clarinet, Violin and Piano (2 copies), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sonata Strofica, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Compositions, 1971, Deux Hymnes de Pierre-Yves Emery, 1971 Sonata Accompagnata por il Violino, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Compositions, 1974, Partita, 1974 Cantante Six, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Compositions, 1975, Concerto sur "Aupres de ma blonde" pour Trmpette, 1975 Threnodie pour Alto, Violoncelle et Orgue, 1975 Sonnwenden, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Compositions, 1977, Sonata for Two Violins and Piano, 1977 Cantante Nine, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Compositions, 1978, Intermezzo Idilliaco, 1978 Quatrieme Trio a Cordes, 1978 String Quartet Four, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Compositions, 1978, Abendlied for Mattias Claudius, 1978 String Quartet Five, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Compositions, 1979, Sonate pour Alto et Piano, 1979 Li T'ai Po's Answer, 1979 Trio for Violine, Cello and Klavier, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Compositions, 1980, Sonata Accompagnata per Fagotto, 1980 Eins und Alles, 1980 Sonata for Ten, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Compositions, undated, Bulow, undated "Quietly Flowing", undated (Box 8, Folder 6)